<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new found stratagem framed in the old forge of Machivilisme, and put upon the inhabitants of the county of Essex. To destroy the army under his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and to inslave all the free-born of England on a sudden: manifested and laid down, in certain animadversions, upon a clandestine, illegall petition, contrived, made, and privatly printed, by a destructive party in London: and then by them sent down to the ministers of the county of Essex, to publish as on the last Lords day, 4. April, to the people, with directions to take their subscriptions in two sheets of paper: which being done: so many of the subscribers as can, are to be desired to meet at Stratford Langton, the 18. instant Aprill, and so to come and present the same to both Houses, as the petition and sense of the whole county :whereas it was never propounded to the county, nor ever heard of among them, before it came down ready in print, from London, to be published by their ministers, in there severall parishes. With certain observations and cautions on the same, conducing to the information, and publick good of the whole Kingdome.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E384_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861957</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861957</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E384[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new found stratagem framed in the old forge of Machivilisme, and put upon the inhabitants of the county of Essex. To destroy the army under his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and to inslave all the free-born of England on a sudden: manifested and laid down, in certain animadversions, upon a clandestine, illegall petition, contrived, made, and privatly printed, by a destructive party in London: and then by them sent down to the ministers of the county of Essex, to publish as on the last Lords day, 4. April, to the people, with directions to take their subscriptions in two sheets of paper: which being done: so many of the subscribers as can, are to be desired to meet at Stratford Langton, the 18. instant Aprill, and so to come and present the same to both Houses, as the petition and sense of the whole county :whereas it was never propounded to the county, nor ever heard of among them, before it came down ready in print, from London, to be published by their ministers, in there severall parishes. With certain observations and cautions on the same, conducing to the information, and publick good of the whole Kingdome.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Published principally for the meridian of the county of Essex, but may serve for all the counties of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "This was scattered abroad in ye Army when ye Commissioners were sent from ye Parlement to disband ym."; "Aprill 18: 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Essex (England) --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Public opinion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A New Found STRATAGEM FRAMED IN THE OLD FORGE of Machiviliſme, and put upon the Inhabitants of the County of Eſſex.</p>
            <p>To deſtroy the Army under his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and to inſlave all the Free-born of England on a ſudden: Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted and laid down, in certain animadverſions, upon a Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine, illegall Petition, contrived, made, and privatly printed, by a deſtructive party in London: and then by them ſent down to the Miniſters of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Eſſex, to publiſh as on the laſt Lords day, 4. April, to the people, with directions to take their ſubſcriptions in two ſheets of paper: which being done:</p>
            <p>So many of the Subſcribers as can, are to be deſired to meet at Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Langton, the 18. inſtant Aprill, and ſo to come and preſent the ſame to both Houſes, as the Petition and ſenſe of the whole County: whereas it was never propounded to the County, nor ever heard of among them, before it came down ready in print, from London, to be publiſhed by their Miniſters, in there ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>With certain Obſervations and Cautions on the ſame, conducing to the information, and publick good of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſalme 37.12, 13.</bibl>
               <p>The wicked plotteth againſt the juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lord ſhall laugh at him: for he ſeeth that his day is comming.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed principally for the Meridian of the County of Eſſex, but may ſerve for all the Counties of England 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114103:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114103:2"/>
            <head>A new found STRATAGEM: Framed in the old Forge of <hi>Machiaviliſme,</hi> and put upon the Inhabitants of the County of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> The which intended, Clandiſtine, diſſembled, deceitfull <hi>Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> (not more ſpetious then treacherous) is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>To the right honourable, the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <head>The humble Petition of the Inhabitants of the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat in alexigencies having freely, &amp; with the firſt engaged themſelves to the uttermoſt hazard of their lives, and exhauſted their eſtates, for the ſupport of the Kingdome, in its native rights, and liberties, &amp; by the bleſſing of God, the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes have been anſwerable in ſome degree to their deſires, by which we ſit in peace and your ſelves in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, with a full poſſeſſion of the hearts of the people, and now fearing leaſt by the miſcarrying on, of the military charges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the neceſſity of the worke, and the ability of the people, now much weakned by a dearth, ſharper then the late devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſword; you ſhould hazard the loſſe of your ſelves, and friends, not ſo much the alienation of their affections (which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114103:3"/>yet. Is not to be neglected) as their diſablity to ſerve you which may ariſe from the Army now on foot, after ſix moneths ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of all hoſtility here, and ſo <hi>bleedingly</hi> called, for to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of another Kingdome:</p>
                        <p>And alſo from ſo numerous a party in this County, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their quarters like to equall all precedent charges, and to ſurmount the worſt, and heavieſt of our former taxes, eſpeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the manner of being impoſed on us</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your Petitioners doe humbly offer to your prudence, the ſpeedy disbanding of the Army, as a plenary expedient againſt the worſt, that in generall may be feared by you and us, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall of it from the County, by which you ſhall continue ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Maſters, and diſpoſers of them, and theirs in all your pious and faithfull undertakings for the future; and that God will aſſiſt you for all your ſafeties, it ſhall be the dayly prayers of your Petitioners.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Certain Animadverſions and Obſervations upon the ſaid Petition.</head>
               <p>O Fooliſh men of <hi>Eſſex!</hi> who hath be witched you? yee did run well, who hath hindred you? for indeed ye were with the firſt, and moſt forward, in aſſiſting the Parliament, for the recovering and regaining our then loſt Lawes and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and (to your everlaſting fame be it ſpoken) yee have (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the narrative part of the Petition) both hazarded your lives, and exhauſted your eſtates, in the common cauſe of the Kingdome; but yee are not alone. And will yee doe and ſuffer all theſe things in vain, if it be yet in vain? Will yee now fooliſhly (through the deluſion of a treacherous party of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt members in both Houſes, and covetuous ambitious Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, who ſeeke by fayned words, and falſe pretences to inſnare, and inſlave you, and to make themſelves Lords over you) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive your ſelves of all the bleſſed fruits which yee are likely, and may (by Gods bleſſing) ſuddenly reape and enjoy? if yee your ſelves doe not let, by being induced cauſleſly to Petition; or act, for the disbanding of that Army, by whom God hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114103:3"/>given you ſuch anſwerable ſucceſſes as your ſelves mention; and cauſed you as yee confeſſe) to ſit in peace, and the Houſe in ſecurity, in which your free acknowledgment, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge you, farre more noble then the Houſe themſelves; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of giving God ſo much glory, or ſhewing themſelves ſo much as verbally thankfull, by any ſuch acknowledgement, they committed Major <hi>Tewledy</hi> the other day, only becauſe he told <hi>Hollis, Earle,</hi> and others in effect, the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid in the pretended Petition <hi>that the Parliament is in full poſſeſſion of the hearts of all the people,</hi> how true this claw-back inſinuation is, I appeale to your own hearts and aske, whether yee do not heare more clamours and complaints then ever heretofore, and doe not ſee more injuſtice, cruelty, and oppreſſions exerciſed and executed by the Parliament, then ever was by the King, and feel more abundant, and heavy preſſures and impoſitions laid upon you, (even to your neceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry food and raiment, and the fruit of your own laboures) then ever were in the worſt of former times? ſo that the people, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor them and all their actions, they are weary of their burdens; and how then can yee affirme that the Parliament, is fully poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of the peoples hearts, when as they are rather poſſeſſed of their hates?</p>
               <p>As for that ſubtill ſuggeſtion of feare, in which is implied a ſpecious pretence of a care to avoid a future inconuenience, <hi>viz. leaſt by carrying on the Military charges beyond the neceſſity of the work</hi> (as if there were now no need of the Army, and that if it was disbanded, yee ſhould be troubled no more with ſuch military taxes and charges) <hi>and the ability of the people,</hi> (as if <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> was ſo poore and eaten up, which hath been leaſt troubled with quartering) <hi>now much weakned with a dearth</hi> (not more I hope then other Countries (<hi>ſharper then the late devouring ſword</hi> (God for bid, doe not bely God) <hi>you ſhould hazard the loſſe of your ſelves and friends, and not ſo much the alination of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as their diſability to ſerve you &amp;c.</hi> It is both groundleſſe and ſenſleſſe for if this Army were now disbanded, the Parliament would ſtill carry on the military charge, by raiſing them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Armies ſtead, and to that end they have both nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114103:4"/>certain officers which they intend to imply therein, and voted the raiſing of 60000 <abbr>l</abbr> a moneth to maintain it and the forces in <hi>Ireland:</hi> So that the taking away this Army, will not take away the military charge from you, and the Parliament it ſeems would never the leſſe hazard the loſſe of your good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and ability to ſerve them, and therefore yee may even ſpare that your great care for them, and it is very probable you may ſuddenly (if you doe not already) find that they have no ſuch great care of you.</p>
               <p>And where it is ſaid that <hi>by quartering ſo many of them, their quarters are like ſhortly to equall all precedent charges, &amp; to ſurmount the worſt and heavieſt of your taxes eſpecially by the manner of their being impoſed on you:</hi> Your Taxes ſure have either been few, and very ſmall in reſpect of others, or elſe the quartering of this Army which is (as I have heard) content with ordinary provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and will not abide I am confident longer then is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient with you, and payeth quarters ſo often as it receiveth pay, cannot amount to ſuch your incomparable prejudice, as thoſe high and hyperbolricall expreſſions <hi>(of amounting and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting)</hi> doe ſound forth, and import: and as for the manner of their being impoſed on you, I doe beleeve it is neither force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, nor diſproportionably: but this particular his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> their Generall (who was never yet taxed for any irregular quatterings) can more diſtinctly anſwer; and ſo I have done with the narative part of your pretended, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Petition.</p>
               <p>Now whereas in the concluſion, or Petitionary part, <hi>ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are humbly to offer the ſpeedy disbanding of the Army, as a plenary expedient, againſt the worſt that may in generall be feared by you and them, and to have it removed out of your County, that ſo the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> (as yee muſt ſay, but I hope doe not wiſh) <hi>may be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Masters and dispoſers of you and yours for the future &amp;c.</hi> I would have you obſerve that here is a <hi>dainty gul,</hi> a notable peece of <hi>machiaviliſme</hi> put upon you, not only to make you the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of removing thoſe, who as they have redeemed your rights and liberties, are alſo ready and willing, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall meanes, as the things now ſtand, to defend and maintain
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114103:4"/>your liberties, and to keep you and yours from ſudden vaſalage and ſlavery; but alſo in plain termes voluntarily to offer your ſelves ſlaves; as, that the Parliament ſhall be the abſolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and diſpoſers of you and yours: I hope yee know better what belongs to your own inherent power and native rights, then to make your ſervants your Maſters, or ſo to own them: as to let your Stewards, have abſolute command over you, and all you have; who by the duty of their places are to give you an account of what they have done for you, and how they have diſpoſed that they have already had of you: Thus much for the opening of the Petition: And now I will ſhew you the illegality, inequality, and ill conſequences thereof, if yee be ſo fond, as to ſubſcribe the ſame, and proceed therein.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the illegallity: That which is to go under the name of a County or Corporation ought to be firſt publickly propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all the Inhabitants of that County or Corporation, that there may be a generall meeting, debate, &amp; conſultation about the matter intended, and to be concluded, by &amp; among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Otherwiſe it is clandeſtine, and ſurruptitious comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rather faction, then publick concurrence &amp; therefore may juſtly be rejected: And ſuch is this Petition; For it was never publickly propounded, nor debated, or conſulted by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> but was (as manifeſtly appears) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly deviſed, and framed by a private party, of Lords and Commons, yea, and ready printed, before the matter was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made known or publiſhed among you; and then it was ſent down to the Miniſters to publiſh on the fourth of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant moneth, with order to take your ſubſcriptions in two ſheetes of paper, now is not here an obtruſion on your privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and immunities, and an illegall, unjuſt and indirect courſe uſed, both in the framing of this petition, and getting your ſubſcriptions? (even juſt ſuch meanes as Parliament men, uſe in the elections of new members) and therefore it is not to be accepted, but the contrivers ought rather to be found out and puniſhed; and again it wants one qualification, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially requiſit, in all Petitions, and much more in ſuch as concerne the publick, and are preſented to the Parliament, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114103:5"/>is; neceſſity of the thing deſired, but this is not <hi>petit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ria,</hi> a neceſſary petition for, if the Parliament intend his Army (as they ſay) for <hi>Ireland,</hi> it is much more neceſſary to keep them in a body intire, then to disband them; for then they will diſperſe, and moſt will depart to their own homes, and never goe upon the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vice: and in caſe they doe not intend or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they ſhall goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> then it is as needfull to keep them together, for ſeeing that the Parliament doe conclude that there is yet a neceſſity of keeping up an Army ſtill with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this Kingdome, is it not better (I pray you) to have this Army which we know, and of whoſe fidelity and Chriſtian behaviour wee have had ſuch ſufficient experiment continued then a new Army raiſed, of I know not whom and what? It may be of ſuch as the generall part of the Earle of <hi>Eſſexes,</hi> or <hi>Maſſies</hi> Brigade, and others were; whoſe ill manners, beſides other unſeen all conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences yee wil unhappily find to be a mountain to your backs, in compariſon of the preſent Mole hill quartrerings.</p>
               <p>And now for the inequality of this Petition it containes mighty earneſt deſires to have this Army ſpeedily disbanded, ſeems to complain greatly of their quarterings; but never moves or mentions one word that their arreares may be paid them, or that from henceforth more conſtant pay may be made them, that ſo they may for the future pay their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> better. Have they deſerved for all they have done (Country-men) for you, and the whole Kingdome, no better reward, then to be disbanded and turned off with nothing? What not ſo much as their due, (the price of their lives) for preſerving of yours? Is this equall? Are yee alſo unjuſt and ingratfull? Aske your daily Threſher, your plow-man, and dayes labourer if they will be contented with the like dealing? A bad iccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; yet let them be comforted; God is their po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on and their great reward.</p>
               <p>As for the evill conſequences of this Petition (or of the like) incaſe yee ſhould perſiſt and proceed therein and that it ſhould (as it ought not to) be granted, they are many &amp; more then I, or you, or the moſt part of this blind Kingdome, doth or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fore-ſee or apprehend but I will only him at one head or two,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114103:5"/>and ſo commend all to the judgements of the world and your conſideration.</p>
               <p>By all appearances (and to me it is viſible) that there is a ſtrong endevour and deſigne by a company of falſe, traiterous, and deceitfull men; in both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of proud, coveteous Prieſts, who have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined in one, for the accompliſhment of their owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination &amp; power over us, ſuddenly to inthrall &amp; inſlave us; that ſo they may keep their abominable actions from being queſtioned, and themſelves from deſerved ſhame and juſtice, and there is no let for them in the way to it but this Army, the which they know right well will not be corrupted, but doth expect to have their Oathes and Declarations fulfilled, and therefore doe theſe ill men work by all means poſſibly to disband and diſſolve it, and in particular by the contriving and ſending you this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to own and ſubſcribe, that they may take thereby a ſeeming juſt cauſe, as deſired of the Country, to proceed in their diſtructive purpoſe, the which if they can bring to paſſe, then will they raiſe up an Army of wicked men, ready, and reſerved for that end, which ſhall be a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army for their defence, in the execution of all their injuſtice and oppreſſions, and by the helpe of the inland Garriſons (whereof I am ſure there is now no need) will they tyrannize (not like Lords and Kings, but worſe then either great <hi>Turke,</hi> or grim <hi>Tarter</hi>) over us: and and where then I pray, is our Lawes and our liberties, for which this Army hath fought; and which they have redeemed for us with their ſword, and for which we have paid ſo deare? And thus yee will have the laſt clauſe of the Petition fulfilled really, to your ſorrow and woe; for yee ſhall not more be ruled by a known Law, as free
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114103:6"/>men of <hi>England,</hi> but curbed and governed by the ſword, as the Peaſants be of <hi>France,</hi> and the inſlaved Bores of <hi>Flanders</hi> who indeed (as your Petition is) are wholly and all they have at their lawleſſe Maſters diſpoſe, Nay they will not tyrannize over your bodies only, but your ſoules alſo; for then you muſt put on the Presbyterian yoake; it is already ſo agreed between them and our dear Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and becauſe they cannot otherwiſe ſet up amongſt us that antichriſtian inſlaving government, they will doe it by the ſword, and ſo we ſhall have a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed, as <hi>Mahomet</hi> eſtabliſhed his <hi>Alchoran,</hi> for if yee will not obey, yee muſt expect either ſmart, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary puniſhment, or deſtroying, impriſonment: and yee may ſee the proud Prieſts footing even in this Petition: is it not commended unto them, and are not they to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt you on a ſudden, and to ſurpriſe your judgements by fained words and ſpeeches? and I beleeve you ſee not their end in it, it is becauſe they know that this Army is generally an enemy to their pride, and pompous Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly livings, crying down their <hi>Diana,</hi> their Tyth-monging and unlawfull calling, whereſoever they come, whereby their trade (for ſo they make their preaching only and alone to be) is in danger to be ſet at naught; and it is by their craft (as <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſaid) that they get their wealth, and therefore would they ſtir up you, under the pretence that the quartering of the Army, is a burden to you, to Petition to have them disbanded, at leaſt to have them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
               <p>But I hope Country-men yee are more wiſe, then to be acted by other mens councels, to father a child that is none of your own, that was formed, borne, amd brought forth, before it came to your knowledge or ſight: can
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114103:6"/>any man tell better then your ſelves, where your ſhooe pincheth you, and what is moſt expedient for you to doe? Never render your ſelves ſo rediculous, as to be led like children and fooles by the noſe; to be made ſtalking horſes for other mens deſignes, whoſe intereſts are diſſonant, and inconſiſtant with yours.</p>
               <p>As for this poor Army, what evill hath it done, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hath it ſo highly offended? for which of all its good deeds is it ſo oppreſſed, deſpiſed, hated, and perſecuted? Is it (when all others falſified) for proving faithfull, or for accompliſhing your deliverance, beyond your own faith or expectation) in ſo ſhort a time? par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them theſe offences, another Nation would doe it, and hold them dear, their very enemies cannot but juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and yet ſo great is their malice towards them; that becauſe they petitioned the Houſe but for their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, an act of indempnity to ſave them harmeleſſe, a more conſtant pay, that they might be able to pay their quarters, and ſome few other moſt juſt and reaſonable things; they unjuſtly declared againſt them in print, as mutinous, and obſtructers to the releife of <hi>Ireland,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (God knowes) there are many thouſands ſpare Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers beſides in this Kingdome, whom they might if they would) ſend thither.</p>
               <p>And when their Officers, Lieutenent generall <hi>Hamond,</hi> Commiſſary <hi>Ireton,</hi> and others appealed to the Houſe: and deſired that theſe malicious ſuggeſtions might be proved, or the Authors puniſhed, and the Army vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; they could not obtain ſo much at civill right, as the authors of theſe falſe aſpertions (which were <hi>Rosſiter</hi> and <hi>Harley</hi>) to be called forth; an act both baſe and ſhamefull but what is to be expected, where juſtice is fortified with impudence.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114103:7"/>
               <p>One word more to you ſweet men of <hi>Eſſex. Whoſe poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery hath this Army deſtroyed? whoſe goods have they ſpoyled, or whoſe ſheep or calves have they ſtolne, or whoſe perſons have they confronted, terrified or abuſed in their Houſes, or what markets have they hindred by robbing of paſſengers, and infeſting the roades and high wayes, as too many others yee knew who have been leſſe provoked, have done? If none of this be done, what juſt cauſe then have yee, I ſay yee, more then all other Counties, where they have been, to complain or petition againſt them? I could tell you: that yee have every man ſat at home under his Vine, and under his fig tree with full tables in peace and ſafety, when theſe poor ſoules have been in the field in the face of death, in froſt, ſnow, rain, cold, heat, wet, and dirt, by day, by night, in hunger and thirſt, to keep back from you, and to ſuppreſſe the fury of your blood-thirſly enemies:</hi> and can you, or any chirſtian man think on this, and ſo ill reward this precious Army? In reaſon it is impoſſible, but experience proves the contrary, ſo full of bitterneſſe, rage and malice, hath the Devill filled the hearts of ſome men againſt them; but of you I have better hopes, preſuming that yee will not be ſo eaſily removed from your own ſteadfaſtneſſe, nor be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through the deluding ſubtilty of any, to act in the leaſt againſt thoſe, who have indured ſo many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, paſſed ſo many perrils, obtained ſo many victories, and never accounted their own lives deare unto them for your ſakes. Whatſoever others may doe, either, through ignorance or malice, yet let it not be ſaid, that the County of <hi>Eſſex</hi> (a County that hath alwaies been eſteemed prudent and religious) did ſhew it ſelfe ingrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or deſpightfull to the preſervers both of their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and lives.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114103:7"/>
               <p>Truly in my thoughts this Army can never be enough requited, for doe wee not at this day, (next under God) by them enjoy all wee have? Have not they ſubdued our enemies, and removed our feares, and cauſed us to dwell in ſafety? And are not they a contented, patient, well governed people, can you ſay that God is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them? then certainly they that hate and deſpite them are of the Devill.</p>
               <p>For my part (Country-men and all others whom it may concern) I hold nothing more expedient for you, and me, and all true Engliſh men (ſeeing the publick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary is ſubdued, and our Parliament ſo averſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to do us juſtice and eſtabliſh our liberties) then to petition forthwith effectually, to have juſtice ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and impartially executed, and our Lawes and liberties eſtabliſhed, and a juſt account rendered of all the monies they have received: and without queſtion when theſe juſt things are done, the Army will of its own accord ceaſe and lay down. I account this that <hi>unum Neceſſarium,</hi> that one neceſſary thing, which is now principally to be minded in the Kingdome, &amp; not to petition about quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings, and removings, and preachings, and places, and any thing indeed, rather then this very, only thing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which all other our outward enjoyments are nothing, was but one thing done (Law, and liberty eſtabliſhed) the wheels of our State would goe eaſily, commands would be pleaſant, diſcontents would be removed, inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, oppreſſion and Treaſon would be baniſhed, and ſupplanting dividing ſpirits would be utterly diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In the meane time till this be done, it is the beſt and only way for the Countries and free commoners of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to preſerve this Army in power and being, and to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114103:8"/>petition that it may ſtill ſtand and be continued, and tha others (rather then it) may be ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> that ſo in caſe theſe juſt demands be denied, contrary to duty, Oath and Covenant, the poore Commons may have a ſhelter and defence to ſecure them from oppreſſion and violence, and his Excellency and every Soldier under him by the duty of his place, and vertue of the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is bound thereunto. Who knoweth whether wee may not yet have as great need of this Army, as we have ever had? For it is evident and all men may ſee, that our native rights and liberties are now in more hazard, then they were at the firſt, and that we are more in jeoperdy, of them by a cloſe trayterous party (our pretended friends) then wee were by our publick profeſſed foes. And our greateſt, and moſt dangerous enemies, are now they of our own Houſe.</p>
               <p>Sweet friends, I am a meer ſtranger to you, but one that am a true lover of my Country, and therefore thought good, as a Member of the ſame body politicke with you, to give you a few animadverſions, with ſome cautions, and obſervations; concerning the ſubtill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, diſſembled practiſes, wherewith your homebred adverſaries, goe about to make you inſtruments of your own miſery and miſchief. And laſtly, mark this I beſeech you and conſider it ſeriouſly.</p>
               <p>Why cannot the Parliament as well ſend over thoſe Officers and Soldiers they have intended for a new Army here, to ſerve in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as theſe of this Army? Can they give the Kingdome a ſatisfying reaſon? It is more then I and many more can apprehend, if they can: But if here ly not a deep miſtery, no better then cloſe treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I am groſly miſtaken. Let none therefore ſo farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114103:8"/>you, as to draw you to petition for the disbanding of this Army, no, both for your honour and ſecurity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance and diſclaime it and all ſuch practiſes and conſpiracies againſt it, for ſuch deeds will ſavour more of ignorance, malice and invie then of any prudence, juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or neceſſity, and whereas in the cloſe of the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is ſaid that the disbanding of this Army is a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedient againſt the worſt in generall that may be feared, let them by no meanes under pretence of benefit, eaſe, or advantage, deceive you, for it is apparent, and will yet be made more manifeſt that the disbanding, or otherwiſe diſſolving of this Army, is the only plenary expedient to render us Vaſſals and ſlaves, to the will of our enemies, and to bring upon us the worſt of miſeries, and that ſuddenly and inſenſibly, for alaſſe we are at the <hi>pit brinke, and ſee not.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
